# **Jonathan Demers**

Montreal, QC, H4J 1K5, Canada jdemers@opcodesolutions.com linkedin.com/in/jonathan-demers-ing Latest version: MD, HTML, PDF

# SENIOR JAVA TECH LEAD

Please consider my candidacy for the role of **Senior Java Tech Lead**. With 20 years experience in software development and over 10 years as senior consultant for multiple businesses, I acquired rich and diversified experience.

This diversity of practical knowledge gives me a clear vision not only on the best technology to accomplish a given goal, but also on the best team structures and strategies to deliver value for your organization and customers.

I am fully bilingual in French and English and I have many sought-after leadership skills, which makes me a great fit for this role. I'd be glad to schedule a time to discuss this position.

Jonathan Demers, Eng.

### **MANAGEMENT PROFILE**

Creative, hands on leader with extensive experience in software engineering. Highly technical, inspiring and motivating model for other leaders and teams. Fast learner, excellent problem solver and strategic decision maker, with natural propensity to perform in fast paced environments. Thorough understanding of both organizational and technical stakes of software development and their relationships.

Leadership	Technical
✓ Organizational Leadership ✓ Strategic Planning	✓ Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC)
✓ Team Coordination ✓ Talent Management ✓ Coaching	✓ Agile Methodologies ✓ Architecture ✓ Distributed Systems
✓ Vision Alignment ✓ Goal Setting ✓ Team Leadership	✓ Design Patterns ✓ REST ✓ SOA ✓ DevOps
✓ Communication ✓ Collaboration ✓ Management	✓ System Integration ✓ Cloud ✓ Development

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# **OpCode Solutions - Leader & Consultant - Software Engineering**

Aug 2008 - Present

Accelerate software development cycle for multiple clients. Consulting services includes organizational leadership, infrastructure & architecture vision, strategy and hands-on execution.

- Leadership: Innovation, Communication, Motivation, Strategic thinking, Problem solving, Decision making, and more...
- Backend: Java, J2EE, Spring, NodeJS, TypeScript, Python, Web services, REST, OAuth, SQL, Linux, Cloud, and more...
- Frontend: React, HTML, JavaScript, TypeScript, Angular, REST, CSS, Bootstrap, and more...

Multiple clients, including (non-exhaustive list):

- NBC Full Stack Dev Lead (2020 Present): Details below
- TD Bank Development Lead (2018 2020): Details below

- Pstox Senior Software Engineer (2017 2018): Development and architecture on ThinkingCapital's online financing platform for businesses, which got successfully acquired by Purpose Financial. Multiple system integrations, including SalesForce and Equifax.
- Morgan Stanley Senior Software Engineer (2015 2017): Details below
- **TERN Financial Group Senior Software Engineer & Architect** (2014 Present): Fully design, develop, host and maintain TERNingpoint quote and policy management system.
- Intact Senior Software Engineer (2013 2014): Development on new insurance policy management system with service oriented architecture (SOA backend). Project: PAS.
- Industrial Alliance Securities Senior Software Engineer (2013): Architecture and development on new fixed income trading platform (Bond Trader). Multiple system integrations, including:
  - o Bloomberg TOMS for real-time price feed and trade capture report over FIX protocol.
  - CBID's trading platform to submit orders and receive executions over FIX protocol.
  - o IBM ISM (SIS) to send phase1 data in real time for DP trades and at EOD via SFTP.
- Desjardins Tech Lead & Senior Software Developer (2012 2013 & 2010 2011): Details below
- **Gemalto (now Thales) Senior Software Engineer** (2011 2012 & 2008 2009): Develop mobile banking and instant messaging solutions on backend and frontend (Android). Improved performance and stability of backend up to 1000 tx/secs.
- **Penson Financial Services Senior Software Developer** (2010): Migrate and enhance several financial applications from IBM ISM platform to Broadridge platform.

Technologies: Java 11, Java 8, J2EE, Maven, Spring, Spring Boot, OSGi, JPA, Hibernate, QuickFIX/J, JSch, Struts, Tomcat, Jetty, Mule ESB EE, Websphere, Jenkins, JMeter, REST, JSON, OAuth2, JWT, Swagger, Auth0, SOAP, JAXB, WSDL, XSD, MySQL, Oracle, MS SQL server, Elasticsearch, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, JQuery, Cloud, AWS, EC2, RDS, VPC, DNS, TLS/SSL, certbot, Linux, Ubuntu, Red Hat, Debian, Docker, Eclipse, Android SDK, Anypoint Studio, RAD, RTC, Git, Jira

# National Bank of Canada - Full Stack Dev Lead (Consultant)

2020 - Present

- Lead agile squad of frontend, backend, SQL and test-automation developers.
- Advise the program management on organizational matters.
- Recruit, onboard, motivate, assign tasks, unblock and evaluate performance of squad members.
- Provide feedback on program architecture solutions.
- Advise on project and delivery planning.
- Facilitate communications between business stakeholders and technical members.

Projects: SOMA. Multiple system integrations, including very legacy systems. Internet facing application.

Technologies: Java 11, Spring Boot, React, TypeScript, Selenium, Microservices, REST, GraphQL, OpenAPI, OAuth 2.0, PKCE, Okta, Sybase, MariaDB, IBM MQ, Camunda, Maven, npm, Linux, Bash scripting, OpenShift, Kubernetes, helm, vault, Harness, Docker, CI/CD, Jenkins, Nexus, Veracode, IQ Server, Git, Splunk, Datadog, Atlassian suite (Bitbucket, Jira, Confluence, etc.), Agile methodology, SAFe.

# **TD Bank - Development Lead (Consultant)**

2018 - 2020

- Lead teams of developers and devops on numerous successful enterprise projects.
- Advise the department senior director on organizational matters.
- Architecture vision and design on new A/B infrastructure.
- Steer the new CI/CD pipeline vision and development.
- Advise on project and delivery planning.
- Facilitate communications between business stakeholders and technical teams.

Projects: GPS 2.1, GPS 2.2 and much more. Multiple system integrations. Buy online. Customer facing applications: Mylnsurance,

#### DigitalQuoter.

Technologies: Java, Spring, Maven, JBoss, OAuth 2.0, REST, Soap, Angular, TypeScript, NodeJS, PM2, npm, VSCode, Oracle, Linux (RHEL), Git, Atlassian suite (Bitbucket, Jira, confluence, etc.), CDN, Private Cloud, CI/CD, Jenkins, Ansible, Docker, Veracode, IQ Server, Agile methodology.

#### **Morgan Stanley - Senior Software Engineer (Consultant)**

2015 - 2017

- Lead, coach and motivate 2 developers. Advise developer performance to software development VP.
- Architecture and development on real-time pricing of fixed income securities and search platform used by financial advisors.

Technologies: Java 8, Scala, Linux, DB2, WebSphere MQ, Spring, Hibernate, Spring, Play, SBT, Git, Autosys, Kerberos, Linux, etc.

#### **Desjardins - Tech Lead & Senior Software Developer (Consultant)**

2012 - 2013 & 2010 - 2011

- Lead backend development of new online trading platform (Stocks, Options, Mutual Funds, etc).
- Provide technical leadership and architecture vision to the software development team.
- Successfully complete migration of existing Java applications to high-available (HA) infrastructure.

Technologies: Java, J2EE, Tomcat, Weblogic, Mule ESB, Spring, JSON, Linux (Red Hat), MySQL, Websphere MQ, ActiveMQ.

#### 5 Employers - Software Developer & Architect

2001 - 2008

From entry-level Developer to Senior Software Developer & Architect. Learnt real-world programming skills and technologies before starting consultation career.

- **Tecsys Solutions Architect** (2006 2008): Develop, architect and customize Supply Chain Management applications for clients. Started as Software Developer in R&D and got promoted to Solutions Architect in Custom Enhancement division.
- Morgan Stanley Systems Architect (2004 2006): Develop distributed financial system for trade allocation of fixed income securities.
- Logient Software Developer (2002 2004): Develop many applications for clients, from CMS to custom E-Commerce solutions.
- Institut de recherche d'Hydro-Quebec Software Developer (2002): Develop real-time software and hardware integration for underwater robot used for the inspection of hydroelectric dams.
- Canadian Space Agency Intern (2001): Develop testbed to measure the performance of spatial RF communication modules.

Technologies: Java, J2EE, Tomcat, JBoss, Websphere, Servlet, Jsp, Taglibs, Html, JavaScript, XML, DTD, XSLT, XPaths, JAX-WS, SOAP, IBM MQSeries, Linux, AlX, Oracle, Informix, Sybase, PostgreSQL, MatLab, C++, Inertial navigation system, Kalman Filter, QNX Real Time OS (RTOS).

### **EDUCATION**

# **University of Michigan - Specialization, Organizational Leadership**

2017 - 2018 Credential ID HRYMS5AB3PTJ

This 5-Star "Leading People and Teams Specialization" from Michigan faculty strengthen essential leadership skills with proven management techniques. It also includes interviews with exceptional leaders Jeff Brodsky, Global Head of HR for Morgan Stanley, and John Beilein, Head Coach of the University of Michigan Men's Basketball Team. The specialization has 5 courses over 20 weeks:

- Inspiring and Motivating Individuals
- Managing Talent

- Influencing People
- Leading Teams
- Leading People and Teams Capstone

Grade Achieved: 99%

# Polytechnique Montréal - B.Eng., Engineering - Telecommunications

1998 - 2002

- Mention of excellence from the general director for academic achievement.
- Scholarship for academic excellence.
- Achieved unconditional admission to PhD directly (skipping Master), I did not pursue this goal.

GPA: 3.8 (max of 4.0 at Polytechnique)

# **CERTIFICATIONS**

#### deeplearning.ai - Artificial Intelligence - TensorFlow in Practice

Certificate Issued 2020 - 4 courses, 16 weeks:

- Introduction to TensorFlow for Artificial Intelligence (Al), Machine Learning (ML), and Deep Learning
- Convolutional Neural Networks (CNN) in TensorFlow
- Natural Language Processing (NLP) in TensorFlow
- Sequences, Time Series and Prediction

Technologies: Python, TensorFlow, Keras, Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib

# deeplearning.ai - Artificial Intelligence - Deep Learning

Certificate Issued 2019 - 5 courses, 16 weeks:

- Neural Networks and Deep Learning
- Improving Deep Neural Networks: Hyperparameter tuning, Regularization and Optimization
- Structuring Machine Learning Projects
- Convolutional Neural Networks
- Sequence Models

Technologies: Python, TensorFlow, Keras, Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib

### MuleSoft - MuleSoft Certified Developer - Integration and API Associate

Certificate Issued 2017 (2 years validity)

# **REFERENCES**

"[Jonathan Demers] is a strong lead who takes full ownership and able to effectively and efficiently communicate to different levels. Jonathan has strong technical background that helps him provide options to technical and delivery problems. I recommend Jonathan and I hope to have a chance to work with him again."

-- George Gouel, Senior manager, Delivery & partner management at TD

"[Jonathan Demers] really help us to deliver multiples projects under his excellent technical and strong delivery skills. He also imposed himself as versatile around whole development reality, technical issues, infrastructure design and configuration. I strongly recommend Jonathan [...]" -- Guillaume Roberge, Senior Manager, Software Development at TD

"Jonathan is efficient, competent and has an excellent knowledge of architecture, design, development and the Java language. He is a key player and person to have on your major project."

-- Aiman Sawan, Founder at Butor

"Jonathan is a quick learner that adapted very well to our work environment. I recommend Jonathan on every team that have challenging problems to solve or critical system to deliver."

-- Tony Bussieres, Chief Technology Officer, Big Data specialist & Co-founder at TickSmith